<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at the anniversay-meeting of the Charter-house scholars at the chappel in the Charter-house, on Monday, December 13th, 1680 / by Nathanael Resbury ...</title>
            <author>Resbury, Nathanael, 1643-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57060</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1130</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36775</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16015149</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16015149</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104756</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57060)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104756)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1155:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at the anniversay-meeting of the Charter-house scholars at the chappel in the Charter-house, on Monday, December 13th, 1680 / by Nathanael Resbury ...</title>
                  <author>Resbury, Nathanael, 1643-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26 [i.e. 28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XXV, 40 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104756:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104756:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACH'D at the ANNIVERSARY-MEETING OF THE CHARTER-HOUSE Scholars: AT THE CHAPPEL IN THE Charter-Houſe. On <hi>Monday, December</hi> 13th. 1680.</p>
            <p>By <hi>NATHANAEL RESBURY,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Wandſworth</hi> in the County of
<hi>Surrey,</hi> and Chaplain to the Right Honorable <hi>Arthur</hi> E. of <hi>Angleſey</hi> Lord Privy Seal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s Head in St.
<hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:104756:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104756:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON ON Matth. xxv. <hi>v.</hi> 40. <hi>And the King ſhall anſwer and ſay unto them, Verily I ſay unto you, In as much as ye have done it to one of the leaſt of theſe my Brethren, ye have done it unto Me.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT hath been a mighty out-cry in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the calumny hath vended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the multitude, like other groundleſs Traditions, that our Religion is ſo meer a brag of Faith, that to ſhow how perfectly it diſclaims all kind of dependance upon the merit of good works, it diſcharges its Profeſſors from all obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of doing them; and had not our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry (whiles govern'd by the Noble and generous principles of a munificent devotion and piety) erected ſuch Monuments of the uſefulneſs and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104756:3"/>excellency of their Religion, we had had no ſuch auguſt fabricks for performing the Solemnities of our Worſhip, as now we have, but had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented our Selves probably with an ungarniſht <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſome neglected upper-room, which the rage and tyranny of the Age, made the Apoſtles and Primitive Chriſtians, through fear of obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, meet in. Much leſs had we known what an Hoſpital had meant, or any uſeful com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities ſupported by the alms and pious diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals of ſuch whom the <hi>Romiſh</hi> faith had inſpir'd to it.</p>
            <p>But this clamour certainly, as it was only rais'd before the reform'd Religion had time or capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of exerting it ſelf in practice in that kind; ſo it were ſtrange if it could be kept up now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt any, but thoſe who have never ſeen, or read of the conſtitutions or manners of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein this Religion is profeſt.</p>
            <p>For as to the former, I mean our Churches, we have had (God knows) too late and ſad an occaſion to ſhow, what the mind conducted by the Proteſtant Faith can do, when with ſo much largeneſs and alacrity we have rebuilt the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches their Helliſh rage had burnt; and exceeded in the decency and ornaments of thoſe places, though not led to it by the blind and ignorant dictates of a fond and unreaſonable Superſtition;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104756:3"/>which we find ſo inconſiſtent with it ſelf, that it can as furiouſly deſtroy thoſe foundations, and lay the whole ſtructure in aſhes, the building of which they have inſiſted on, as one plauſible ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for their Religion, and the devotion of their Anceſtry.</p>
            <p>As to the latter, I mean the erecting of Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, and conſtituting other uſeful Societies from the mighty ſupplies which the good and well-diſpos'd minds of thoſe within our Church have thought fit to adminiſter. Were it worth the while to enumerate what foundations have been laid for the poor and diſabled in Hoſpitals and Alms-houſes, for education and encouragement to the ingenuous in Schools and Colledges, for the painful and induſtrious in Corporations and Work-houſes, for the maintenance of thoſe that attend at the Altars, and miniſter in Holy things; in a word, what large and profuſe iſſues have been from the wealth and charity of ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelves, for all the juſt uſes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies of life, from the time of the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation to this day, it would be found there hath been as much life in our faith, for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of Good Works, as ever hath been in any one Age of the Church, ſince the time that a community of goods, made the mutual love of Primitive Chriſtians, ſo great and remarkable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:104756:4"/>
            <p>And amongſt the reſt, I may very well ſay that this very Place, the memory of whoſe Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der we celebrate this day, becomes a ſtanding eviction to the knavery of that calumny, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Proteſtant Religion hath been ſcandaliz'd, as a cold, and barren, and empty name, that hath nothing of the thing or ſubſtance of good works in it. A Foundation this is, which having been firſt laid without any other Miniſtry, but that of one ſingle Purſe; and having had no other im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements, but what the products within it ſelf, may have ſwell'd and increas'd it to; is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all the inſtances that can be elſewhere gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, either at home or abroad; no one place in <hi>Europe</hi> probably, or within the whole diffuſions of Chriſtianity, having either beforehand ſet the like Copy, or wrote after this, ſince; the Summ total of this Charity amounting to a far larger ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count (as it hath ſerv'd to much greater pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes) than that Cloyſter of <hi>Carthuſians,</hi> which formerly had, to ſo idle and miſtaken uſes, neſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led here.</p>
            <p>It is true, the Principles have not been the ſame upon which have been grounded this, or other Foundations of our Proteſtant Charity, with what have influenc'd thoſe in the Church of
<hi>Rome;</hi> nor have there been thoſe wretched arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices us'd, as conſequent to thoſe principles, by
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104756:4"/>which the Brokers for the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Charity have been ſo ſucceſsful in the ſolicits they have made for the revenues of it. We have not firſt poſſeſt the World with any frightful perſwaſions about the Torments of a Purgatory, pretending it the lot of moſt Men to paſs through the refinings of that fire into the ſtate of the bleſſed; and that the Prayers of ſome devout Perſons ſecluded from the World to that purpoſe, together with ſome other Miniſtries, will haſten the diſpatches of thoſe Souls from thence, who have had the devotion, and the fortune to give liberally to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the maintenance of ſuch Chauntries.</p>
            <p>We have no Doctrines that teach any expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory and atoning merit in ſuch works as theſe, ſo as to give us the opportunity of ſcrewing out of the confeſſions of ſome ſinners, ſuch Sums for commutation of Penance, or ſatisfaction to Divine Juſtice as may build a Monaſtery or add to the ſupports of one already built. We erect no Foundations upon the Sins of the People; we diſmiſs not the Soul of the unruly Tyrant, who hath beſmear'd himſelf with the bloud of numberleſs Innocents, and rais'd his dominion upon the Necks of juſt Proprietors, we diſmiſs not ſuch an one with this appeaſement of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, under all the horrors of his butchery and injuſtice, that might reaſonably rack and torment
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104756:5"/>him; <hi>if you build ſuch a Religious houſe, or give ſo much into the Treaſury of the Church, you will find your ſelf abſolv'd there, and ſo all the ſcores of bloud and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation wip'd out for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We do not tell the infamous Lecher, that hath done infinite injuries to Families by his boundleſs luſt, and made himſelf a ſtink and abhorrence, by the Diſeaſe that Vengeance allots to that Vice, we do not tell ſuch an one, that his Charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward a Nunnery (where the vow'd chaſtity of thoſe Secluſes may recompence for his beaſtli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) will ſecure his forgiveneſs in the other World, and his reputation in this; Whereas in truth, that very Convent which the Money of ſuch a Wretch may have endow'd or augment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, may prove his Heir in his filthineſſes, as well as his eſtate; and by a Pile of Skuls of the poor murder'd Infants (begot in thoſe ſecrecies of Villany) may raiſe a proper and adequate Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument to the Luſt of the firſt Founder.</p>
            <p>We do not pretend that thoſe Goods, which the Rapine of ſome hath unjuſtly extorted from the right owners, or which the prodigious ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice of others hath congeſted to the ſcandal and reproach of himſelf, or the injury of his relatives; that ſuch, if converted to Religious uſes, when the fate of the Poſſeſſor hath ſet him for ever out of the reach of them, will make him ſuch
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104756:5"/>friends here, and above too, that the Prayers of the one, and the intereſt of the other ſhall lodge him ſafely enough in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s boſom.</p>
            <p>No, the undeſigning plainneſs of our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, ſo directly ſuited to the ſimplicity of the Goſpel, hath laid bare all the cheats and wheadles of that kind; and by propounding and clearing up all the true notions of repentance and faith, and a good life, have made all that ſort of diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſo thin and airy, that we have made our ſelves uncapable of Juggling by ſuch artifices; and what acts of charity are now perform'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us; as they are always deſign'd toward the beſt and moſt uſeful purpoſes of life; not for the ſatiating of ſome lazy Monks, or idle Goſſips, whoſe ſloth, and whoſe plenty, inſtead of the Divine and contemplative life, which they pretend, expoſeth them to all the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of luſt and wantonneſs: as (I ſay) the acts of our Charity have not this tendency, but to better deſigns, ſo they are grounded from better Principles, and promoted by more Chriſtian per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions in the breaſts of the Donors.</p>
            <p>The intentions of our charity are chiefly dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted againſt Idleneſs the Nurſery of all Vices: or toward the relief of ſuch Perſons whom po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104756:6"/>or other misfortunes may have reduc'd to the extremeſt diſablements: or, in a word, the inſtitution of ingenuity in Youth, or compoſure of thoughtfulneſs and ſolicitude in old Age, that ſome after a long and cumberſome part acted, may have the advantage of retiring themſelves, where, freed from the cares or the hazards of this life, they may in all repentance and devotion make up the reckonings betwixt their Souls and God, and fit themſelves for the Summons they muſt expect at his Bar: and of ſuch a Nature is this great and almoſt unparallel'd Foundation, where ſo many Youths may be ſhap'd and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell'd for ſervice in the World, and ſo many aged Gentlemen drawn off and eas'd after the ſervice they have done, and put into circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wherein they need be thoughtful about no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Immortality.</p>
            <p>The Principles of which (no queſtion) were, that Humanity and Brotherly love which the Chriſtian Religion eſpecially teacheth; that truſt and ſtewardſhip which we are told in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, is repos'd in great and rich Men; that affinity and kindred, which bounty and merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs hath with all other parts of goodneſs and righteouſneſs, and, to add no more, that relation and nearneſs which the Founder of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104756:6"/>the Bleſſed Jeſus, the Man-Chriſt doth own with thoſe of our natures, transferring the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of all good turns done to one another, as done unto himſelf; for ſo it is in the words of my Text, <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, In as much as ye have done it unto one of the leaſt of theſe my brethren, ye have done it unto Me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words are part of the repreſentation which our Lord makes of his appearing in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at the end of the World, where he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces the different Sentence upon thoſe on the
<hi>right hand,</hi> and <hi>on the left;</hi> The former he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates in all the glories <hi>of a Kingdom prepared for them from the foundations of the World, v.</hi> 34. The latter he baniſheth from his preſence and all the bliſs of it, <hi>into everlaſting fire prepared for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and his Angels, v.</hi> 41. And the account of this different ſentence alledg'd and explain'd: <hi>viz.</hi> the good deeds that thoſe on the <hi>right hand</hi> had done, in feeding the <hi>hungry</hi> and relieving the <hi>ſtranger,</hi> clothing the <hi>naked</hi> and
<hi>viſiting the ſick:</hi> and the neglects that thoſe on the <hi>left hand</hi> had been guilty of, in all thoſe excellent ſervices which they had the obligation and opportunity of performing: à <hi>v.</hi> 35. <hi>ad finem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall take no occaſion here to make any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104756:7"/>upon this great Court of Judicature, nor conſider the nature of the Proceſs: I ſhall not determine for or againſt the conjecture of the learned <hi>Grotius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lactant. Hieron. Theophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lact.</note> who would ſuppoſe (for which he alſo cites ſome conſiderable Fathers for ſtrengthening his preſumption) that this Scene of judgment ſeems only laid for the Chriſtian World, whiles they that either had not known God, or rejected his Goſpel, were by their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief <hi>condemn'd already.</hi> All that I ſhall do, ſhall be with a direct eye upon what ſuits with the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and reaſons of this Aſſembly, wherein ſome of us that have in this place had our firſt inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Youth, and others of us that have had with our Education, our Maintenance too, do unitedly meet to recognize that bulky charity of our Founder, that hath given us the opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of either. So that becauſe throughout this whole Scene of action repreſented in the laſt Judgment, we may obſerve, partly that no other inſtances of life are mention'd or inſiſted on, but the extent or defect of Mens charity or good deeds; and partly the mighty acknowledgments which the Great Judge makes of ſuch good deeds, as if the performance or neglect redoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon himſelf; I ſhall make this communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative charity the ſubject of my remaining Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and as briefly as I can diſpatch what
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104756:7"/>I have to ſay under two or three Heads, which may abundantly vindicate the Doctrines and the effects of the Proteſtant Faith, as by no means foreign to Good Works.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, there is no duty or performance in the whole Chriſtian Law more expreſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd and inſiſted on, than this of Alms-giving, or doing good to thoſe that ſhall ſtand in need of it. This, I might argue, without muſtering up the various injunctions in the Goſpel, that look this way, from what we find urg'd in my Text, that our Bleſſed Lord ſhould account ſuch works, of ſo weighty an importance, that he makes it his
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or the ground of his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, to abſolve or condemn Mankind accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to what they have done or not done in this kind. He does not here inſiſt on the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxy of their Religion, what Principles or Party they had eſpous'd, how demurely they had liv'd, what numbers or length of Prayers they had wonted themſelves to, how many Faſts they had kept, or Sermons they had heard, (though herein the anſwer of a good conſcience will be abundantly valuable at that day) but the reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is made upon the viſits that have been given to the ſick, what clothing to the naked, what food to the hungry, what protection and relief
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104756:8"/>to the oppreſs'd and indigent? after which Copy the Apoſtle writes, when he tells us that this is the Religion indeed; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>Pure Religion and undefiled before God and the Father, is this, to viſit the Fatherleſs and Widows in their affliction,</hi> &amp;c. It is a cheaper and eaſier performance to maintain a ſemblable regard for the duties of the firſt Table in our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions toward God, than this coſtly and active part of love toward our Neighbour, as compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in the ſecond Table of the Law. There were thoſe in our Saviour's time, who, while they were <hi>devouring Widows houſes,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.14.</note> could, in that very <hi>pretence be making long prayers,</hi> and it was Saint <hi>Baſil</hi>'s obſervation ſince that;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baſ. M. in Luc.</hi> 12.8.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>I have known ſome that could faſt, and pray, and groan, and be very dextrous at all the guiſes of a cheap and unexpenſive Religion, and yet they have not the heart to give one Farthing to the Poor.</hi> There is nothing new under the Sun; the obſervation both of our Saviour's and this Father's, is as freſh and pertinent (God knows) in the Age we live in as ever.</p>
            <p>But however diſproportion'd the lives of ſome Chriſtians are, or have been to their Law of Faith; yet have they no more explicit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104756:8"/>in any thing than in this: Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour having not only adopted the Moral Law into his, as he hath ſumm'd it up under thoſe two great heads of <hi>love to God</hi> and
<hi>love to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.37-39.</note> but alſo explain'd and extended the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of that part that concerns our Neighbor, even to the
<hi>loving our enemies,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.44.</note> and <hi>doing good to thoſe</hi> that have wiſht or done us hurt. So gentle, ſo good natur'd a Religion indeed became him whoſe errand into the World was to accompliſh a charitable work which goes beyond the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of Angels to indict juſt praiſes to.</p>
            <p>To ſay the truth, this Law of Charity is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparably indented in humane nature, to which indeed though the whole Chriſtian Law (ſo far as it concerns our practice) does bear a ſuitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and correſpondency, yet doth this inſtance of it ſeem more immediately connate and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, as in relieving any perplext and diſtreſs'd part of humane Nature, we labour in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is Natural, that is, the preſervation of ſelf, which whiles we withdraw from, we are in ſome meaſure in that unreaſonable confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy repreſented in
<hi>Menenius Agrippa</hi>'s Apologue, where the reſt of the Members would withhold their miniſtries from the belly till the whole ſtarv'd.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:104756:9"/>
            <p>And as it is a Law engraven even in humane Nature as ſo, ſo let me add, that it is an eternal Law, that is, it hath the eternal and unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able reaſons of good in it, <hi>viz.</hi> of doing good where the neceſſities of an occaſion ſhall offer. It is true indeed, ſuch was not the original frame and diſpoſure of Mankind, but that had it not been for the depravation of humane Nature, this Law of Beneficence might have been ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeded for ever. Providence was not unequal in the proviſions it made, but as the Sun and the Stars which were always out of the reach of the Ambitious or the Envious, do ſtill diffuſe their univerſal heat and influence, according to their firſt ordinance and appointment, ſo would all the riches and products of the Earth and of the Sea have indifferently ſubſerv'd for the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ſupply of all Mortals, there being enough in the boſom and repoſitory of Nature for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one to have fetcht his ſufficiencies; but Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition and Rapine made the Invaſion, and ſince that, Power and cunning hath ſecur'd the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſt, Divine Providence having ſo far inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd for the order and government of the World, as to make the liberality of thoſe who find themſelves plentifully poſſeſt, where they diffuſe it toward the attempering the extreme wants of others, and the patience and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104756:9"/>of thoſe whoſe boundaries are more nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and ſtraiten'd, equally a vertue, and equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly well-pleaſing in his ſight. And this is that now, which makes up the lovely harmony and gives the beauty of agreement in things ſo wide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly different and diſproportion'd; when the poor can in a ſtill and quiet ſubmiſſion both ſerve and depend upon the Rich, and the Rich do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat the expectations of the Poor, but (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle expreſſes it, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.14.) <hi>one Man's abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance ſupplies another man's wants,</hi> and in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <hi>makes the equality.</hi> It was a generous expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of him in <hi>Seneca; Ego mea ſic habeo ut omnium ſint.</hi> I do ſo far poſſeſs what I have, that it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ones elſe.</p>
            <p>Hence in that oeconomy amongſt the <hi>Jewes,</hi> which was ſo peculiarly of God's immediate diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing and regulation, we find the thirtieth part of every Man's in-come (as may be collected from the various tythings allotted for the Poor) was the <hi>ultimum quod ſic;</hi> the very leaſt of a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary charity that muſt be ſet apart for the relief of the needy, and the obſervation of that cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity run into the account of juſtice and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; he was not an honeſt man that would not be punctual and ſtrict in it: he was one of an evil eye (as the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Authors expreſs it) that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104756:10"/>extended not his bounty to ſomething conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably more. To which purpoſe (perhaps) we may conjecture the reaſon why, when our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Law inſiſts upon ſuch ſtrict and repeated commands for our charity, it preſcribes no ſtated meaſures for it; becauſe it would not ſuppoſe us bounded by any of the ſcantlings which former Laws have intimated. But, firſt, we have infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely greater examples before us, than had ever yet been propounded to the World; ſuch was the Lord of Life and Glory himſelf, <note place="margin">2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 8.9.</note> who <hi>though he was rich, yet for our ſakes became poor, that we through his poverty might be made rich.</hi> He emptied himſelf of all that he was veſted in, or had a title to, as to all the riches of his Kingdom above, with all the imaginable grandeurs of this World below, that by this voluntary beggary of his own, we, who had been ſo helpleſly and fatally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſht, might be not only reſtor'd to our ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal honours, but to an Inheritance with Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, beyond all degrees what we could have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to.</p>
            <p>Such was that other inſtance of a large and unbounded Charity in the firſt Chriſtians, who, to ſhow how much this was the Doctrine and Life of the Religion they had engag'd in, did quit their own properties ſo far, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 4.34, 35.</note> where they had
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104756:10"/>any, as by equal portions only, to ſhare with the indigent Brotherhood; that (as the Apoſtle ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies the paſſage of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> gathering <hi>Manna</hi> in the Wilderneſs) <hi>He that had gather'd much, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.15.</note> had nothing over, and he that had gather'd little had no lack.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as we have ſuch tranſcendent examples built upon the Doctrines of Charity in our Law of Faith, ſo we may ſuppoſe our ſelves under obligations of larger diſplays of this vertue, than any other Law had yet directed Men to. Which conſiderations probably, (beſides the exigencies which the Church in its perſecuted ſtate muſt needs conflict with, before it had the Patronage of Kings and Emperours) might fill the Pens of the ancient Writers with ſuch large and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate Exhortations to Charity; In ſo much that ſometimes they charge ſuch with rapine that convert what they have, beyond meer neceſſaries, to their own uſe; and therefore repreſent the richeſt Men but ſuch Stewards, who are to make their Accounts to the Poor for all redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancy, beyond what themſelves may modeſtly need; and at other times do Rhetorically bring the Poor upon the Stage, as claiming his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety in that Silk, or that Gold wherein the gaudy Chriſtian will ruffle it; in thoſe diſguiz'd, and various Meſſes, wherein the humorſome ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104756:11"/>will play the wanton even to a ſurfeit, as part of which ſhould have cloath'd his naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and reliev'd his hunger, and the unjuſt waſt muſt therefore be accounted for at another Bar. Theſe things, however perhaps too ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely ſpoke, at leaſt not to paſs current without the clearing up of ſome caſes, which time will not allow to be at preſent diſcuſs'd; yet are in thus much ſignificant, that they teach us what ſenſe the Ancients had of their obligations to Charity from the Laws of Chriſtianity, and that we have indeed no boundaries to its diffuſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but only the prudent conſiderations of our dependencies, that neither our ſelves nor they ſhould really ſuffer, or be impoveriſh'd, through our unſeaſonable liberalities; and yet even as to this we are prevented all needleſs and unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able fears, by the warranty it hath pleas'd God to give us, both by his Word and Providence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As there is no duty which is more expreſly preſcrib'd by the Chriſtian Law, than this of Charity, ſo there are no encouragements want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to excite us to a chearful performance of it, although we ſuppoſe no expiation or attonement for ſin, no merit or deſert from God by the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt we can do in it. It is very true, that ſuch are our circumſtances with God, through an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104756:11"/>guilt that hath made us ſo obnoxious, that after all we can do,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.10.</note> 
               <hi>we muſt needs ſay we are unprofitable ſervants.</hi> Sin is of that nature, that it makes every action of the man who is imbas'd and deprav'd by it, to be (in ſtricteſt account with God) unlovely and unacceptable; and no future performances can make up for the defects of former, becauſe the utmoſt of all was due at firſt: However, if we are not amongſt the meer Mercenaries and ſtipendiaries in Religion, we may find thoſe encouragements to this vertue, which may render all the wheadles of
<hi>ſatisfaction</hi> or <hi>merit</hi> needleſs and inſignificant toward the making us converſant and exemplary in it.</p>
            <p>As to this, I would not uſe the argument of applauſe and acceptation amongſt Men, becauſe this is a qualification in our Charity which our Bleſſed Lord hath expreſly preſcrib'd againſt; though at the ſame time he aſſures us this is an inſeparable reward to it. We ſhould not <hi>blow the Trumpet before our Alms,</hi> to be ſeen and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded by Men, though if we ſhould do ſo, we ſhould hardly miſs of that reward. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, they have their reward.</hi> This is an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency that hath ſo univerſal an acceptation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Men, that he that hath the moſt aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd it himſelf, either commends, or envies it
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104756:12"/>in another; and the Philoſopher ſpoke ſmartly enough when he told the Children of his Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor, that he ſtood upon even ground with their Father for all his munificence, becauſe he had given him the credit of it; for all Men ſpake well of him for his bounty to <hi>Xenocrates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this is a thought unworthy the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and therefore ought not to be urg'd in this place. However, may I not intimate ſomething of the natural pleaſure that always lives and glowes in the mind thus employ'd? As it is hardly ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the humane Nature, but it muſt be uneaſie and afflicted in whatſoever it ſeems miſerable in its own kind, ſo there is as immediate a joy and well-pleaſedneſs of mind where we are in the leaſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental in its eaſe and relief. To make the ſad and dejected countenance put on ſmiles; not only to ſtill his groans, but turn them into laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and to change the complaints and murmurs of the Poor reduc'd Caitiff into Thankſgivings to Providence, good wiſhes and bleſſings to our ſelves, which perhaps may mingle with our own Prayers (as thoſe of the devout
<hi>Centurion</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare a ſpeedier deſcent of ſome ſignal good to us;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 10.4.</note> what can be more inwardly delightſome and agreeable to a well temper'd mind than this is? There is no good mind that can forbear ſharing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104756:12"/>in anothers joys, and intereſting it ſelf ſo far in all the good dews that fall, though they reach not his own fleece, that even the pleaſure he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives in anothers happineſs, does ſtill derive ſomething of it to himſelf. It was the Angelical temper, to unite in one tranſported Quire, and make their Songs give notice to the World how rejoyc'd they were in the behalf of Man when His <hi>Saviour was born:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi>
2.13, 14.</note> And it is a part of their good natur'd Heaven ſtill, that they can frame a new
<hi>joy at the converſion of a ſinner.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.10.</note> Much more may it reflect a grateful touch upon the mind, when the Man himſelf hath been the Benefactor. This is a God-like complacency, when our own full and entire happineſs, gives us not that reſt and content, but that we muſt be endeavouring, what in us lies, to make others ſo: God himſelf reſted not in the perfections of his own bliſs, till he had created beings to whom he might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, and make them happy in ſome deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative effluxes of himſelf: and the <hi>Bleſſed Jeſus</hi> would fill up that eternity of delight he had in the <hi>boſom of his Father,</hi> with the pleaſure he took in that unſpeakable act of Grace, ſaving Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, by interpoſing himſelf betwixt the ſtroke and death. It is an indication of the real joys that attend every act of beneficence, when it hath been ſo much delight to the ever bleſſed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104756:13"/>God himſelf to be thus doing good. <hi>Epicurus</hi> who made pleaſure his God, yet declar'd this to be a part of that pleaſure, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to be doing good; and he that was God himſelf, that had lain in the boſom of Pleaſure from all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, left this as one of his Maxims when he taught in the World, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> quotes from him, either by the help of Tradition or Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20.35.</note>
               <hi>Remember the words of our Lord Jeſus, how he ſaid, It is more bleſſed to give than to receive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I may add (amongſt many others) laſtly, the grand encouragement in the Text, that our Lord, the Judge himſelf will not diſdain to own the good that we have done to any other, as if it had been done unto himſelf. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>He is not aſham'd</hi> to own the leaſt of his ſervants under the name and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of <hi>his brethren;</hi> and to ſuch (whiles we do it with regard to that relation and affinity with him) he tells us elſewhere that a <hi>Cup of cold water</hi> is regiſtred as a gift that ſhall be accounted for, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.42.</note> when the rewards come to be diſtributed.</p>
            <p>Oh! wondrous condeſcenſion, that the <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Jeſus</hi> ſhould proclaim himſelf ſtill walking in rags, or ſhackled in a Dungeon, and that whiles we are feeding the Beggar, we make Chriſt our Gueſt! who would not gladly pare off all his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104756:13"/>ſuperfluities of life, that he might always have ready an entertainment for ſo great a Perſonage when he craves an alms? Had <hi>Abraham</hi> known the quality of his Gueſts while he invited Angels in, he would not have thought his whole ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance a competent entertainment: We have the word of our Lord himſelf for it, and may be ſure we are treating Him, whiles we relieve the real ſufferer that craves it in his Name. <hi>In as much as ye have done it to one of the leaſt of theſe my brethren, ye have done it unto me.</hi> What an infinite honour is it to be capable thus of <hi>laying up our Treaſures in Heaven?</hi> to cloth and feed him <hi>whoſe is the Earth with all its fulneſs?</hi> to relieve and viſit him whoſe is Heaven it ſelf with all its Joys and Glories? It might well be eſteem'd one of the ſeverer parts of the Eccleſiaſtical cenſure in the firſt ages of Chriſtianity, not to ſuffer ſome kind of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to caſt in their charity into the offertory; and ſo
<hi>Epiphanius</hi> tells us, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>We accept of no offerings from unjuſt or wicked men, but from thoſe that live well.</hi> It was too great an honour for ſuch to be permitted to give good Men their alms, or that ſuch whom Chriſt had ſo near a relation to, ſhould be behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his enemies.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:104756:14"/>
            <p>Theſe Conſiderations (I ſay) give Charity and good Works ſo high an eſtimate, that if we ſeriouſly entertain'd them, we need not, with the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> make lies our refuge, or make uſe of their lewd arguments from <hi>merit,</hi> or <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> or a quicker diſpatch from Purgatory, to animate to well-doing, becauſe there are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient encouragements, we might derive from hence, which none but the Infidel or moſt aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd Senſualiſt would account trivial, and not worthy to be govern'd and perſwaded by.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, There are ſome fair and plauſible appearances of this Charity, which yet really and indeed ought not to be eſteem'd as ſo, becauſe they anſwer not the true purpoſes and ends of it. We have ſome inſtances amongſt our ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which our Laws have wiſely provided; ſuch are our idle wanderers, who, though they may have the Plea of hunger, and cold, and naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to urge and perſwade our compaſſion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them, yet having hands, and health, and ſtrength, which by their own induſtry might la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour out a ſupply to themſelves, our Laws for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the encouragement of ſuch, and that upon the great Apoſtolical Foundation, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.10.</note> that <hi>if any would not work, neither ſhould they eat.</hi> Theſe are not within the kindred of our Bleſſed Lord:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104756:14"/>Though he was poor, yet was not he idle and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active himſelf,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 10.38.</note> but ſpent his whole life in the <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of love: He went about doing good;</hi> and ſo he expects from all his <hi>houſhold of faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon which occaſion, I might again reflect upon moſt of the Religious Foundations in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> Perhaps the riſe and original of ſuch, might of old have been warrantable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; whilſt the Devotioniſt in thoſe Societies had the real opportunities of withdrawing from the World, and contemplating the future ſtate; and by ſevereſt mortifications and ſelf-denial at home, as alſo induſtrious and exemplary inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions abroad might put himſelf and others into a ready poſture for another World: this was to the true purpoſes and ends of Charity, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever by their beneficence begun or encourag'd ſuch foundations as theſe, will be own'd by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as having ſerv'd and ſupply'd Him in <hi>thoſe his Brethren.</hi> But what ſhall we ſay now to thoſe Nurſeries either of Scandal or Miſchief, into which the Religious-houſes abroad are even U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſally perverted? where either the luxury and luſt of a pamper'd and well-fed Monk, the wantonneſs and dalliances of an idle and unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Nun, hath been the ſcoptick theme of witty and obſerving Men for ſome Ages. Or elſe if
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104756:15"/>in other Societies they make not idleneſs their choice, and pretend not ſo much to the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plative, as to the buſie and active life; what is the reſult of this induſtry, (eſpecially in theſe laſt Ages of Jeſuitiſm) but ſearching into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils of Kingdoms, and States, and labouring out a miſchievous intereſt from the intelligence they gain: perplexing and involving the World in Wars and Bloud; making the Thrones of Kings either unſafe or uneaſie, contriving Subverſions of Government, or Helliſh Maſſacres, and all for advancing the Tyranny and Pride of an Apoſtate <hi>Prelate,</hi> to whoſe obedience and intereſts they have bound and oblig'd themſelves, by Vows as impious as Hell it ſelf could invent. The found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and endowing ſuch confederacies as theſe, is ſo far from doing good to the <hi>brethren,</hi> that it will be found at laſt a maintenance and ſupport to the enemies of the <hi>Holy Jeſus;</hi> however they may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe and preſume upon that Name of his to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh the fraternity.</p>
            <p>But, thanks be to God, it is not ſo with us in any of our foundations of Charity; it is leaſt of all ſo, in this, which we at preſent commemorate.</p>
            <p>Here the Parent is disburthen'd from the cares and expences of his Child's education, and hath a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104756:15"/>moral aſſurance from the firſt entry and admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of him here, that he is not only provided for, but likely to act a very uſeful and ſerviceable part upon the Stage of this World, either in the Church or in the Commonwealth. And here old age may compoſe it ſelf, and having diſintangled it ſelf from all the buſtles and the ſnares of an active employ'd life, may be at leiſure to look backward, and repent of all the miſcarriages of times paſt, and in doing ſo, may look forward with a well-grounded hope of cloſing up the whole in peace and bliſs. Oh what a Crown of Joy is it likely to prove to our Founder, at the laſt great Solemnity, when he ſhall ſtand at the head of a numerous happy croud, who have had the opportunities of living uſefully, and dying ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfully, through the miniſtry of that ſignificant charity of his!</p>
            <p>Let me therefore, as an upſhot to this diſcourſe, beſpeak both the Youth and the Age of this place, that you would in your different ſpheres and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities think your ſelves more peculiarly oblig'd by the bounty of this great Man, and kind allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Providence in giving you a ſhare in it; to anſwer the ends and deſigns of it; the young ones, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>in remembring your Creator now in the days of your Youth,</hi> improving the advantages you have both
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104756:16"/>for Learning and Piety, that His Memory may live in the fragrant ſavours of your Lives, and others may be encourag'd to multiply ſuch works, when they diſcern ſuch excellent effects of it in you. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 13.</note> And you Fathers, the
<hi>Keepers of whoſe houſe do</hi> now begin to <hi>tremble;</hi> The decays of whoſe age aſſure you that the flame of life is dwindling and almoſt ſpent off; However you may have liv'd, make it your whole buſineſs to dye well: Let no pretended cares of life divert you, becauſe the unlabour'd liberalities that feed and cloth you now have ſuperſeded all; but, as you are in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Nature haſtening to the endleſs ſtate; ſo take hold of this ſeaſon of leiſure and retirement for making up your laſt periods in that devotion and ſeriouſneſs, that when the great Judge ſhall come to reckon up the good deeds of our migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Benefactor, your ſelves may be amongſt the Number he ſhall point at, when he owns that they were <hi>done to theſe his brethren.</hi> Which God of his infinite mercy grant, through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord, to whom with Himſelf and Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, be given all Praiſe and Glory for ever. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men!</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
